[Music]
this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at se-
radio.net se radio is brought to you by
the it computer society and by It
software Magazine online at computer.org
software developers got some extra time
on your hands use it to learn a new
database inner systems Iris allows you
to choose your language tools and
environment so you can collaborate build
faster and deploy more efficiently now's
your chance to try out inner systems
Iris the fastest way to build
applications Ready Set code visit inner
systems.com Iris to learn
more welcome to software engineering
radio I'm your host Gavin Henry and
today my guest is Tim sneath Tim leads
product management for flutter and dart
working from Google's office in Seattle
he joined Google in 2017 after 17 years
leading client platform and developer
teams at Microsoft in his spare time he
Tinkers with various retro Computing
projects battles with the New York Times
crossword and attempt to persuade his
mother that customers aren't out to get
her Tim welcome to the software
engineering radio is there anything in
your bio that I miss that you'd like to
add uh no I I think you there you hit a
lot of uh interesting things there yeah
I've been uh um playing with computers
since I was a little boy a Wei boy in uh
I grew up in in England and uh my very
first computer was a zx81 and uh it's
it's funny because I still have that
computer literally in my drawer and
every now and again I get it out and
just marvel at how Computing has changed
so much over the last uh years we've
living through an incredible time of of
you know Evolution that I think in a 100
years time people will uh look back and
Marvel at so uh yeah retro Computing has
been my my thing for a little while and
and retro doesn't really take that long
to become retro nowadays does it that's
very true although uh it seems like you
know there's there's a growing lifespan
for computers with you know the decline
of Mo's law and with the way that uh uh
you know various different uh um
efficiencies are are shifting in terms
of what performance looks like it does
seem that you know people have computers
that that are seven years old and that
wasn't the case you know at any other
point in my life it's uh interesting to
see how how things are shifting and
probably will continue to shift so
during the show we will mainly be
talking about the architecture of
flutter however I'd like to start with
an overview of crossplatform development
flutters history and the dark
programming language so Tim what is
crossplatform
development well that's a very broad uh
space of course because uh people have
been building software that runs across
multiple platforms for almost as long as
software has been around right I mean
you know Unix is was a crossplatform or
was written to run on different uh
Computing architectures and Hardware so
the broad in the broad scheme of things
all we're talking about here is is
writing software that isn't tied to a
single um operating system or or device
as think about uh flutter though and we
think about mobile technologies and
crossplatform in in this uh specific
domain uh really what it means is uh
that when you're building you know UI
when you're building uh user experiences
being able to take uh take those
experiences to different kinds of uh
device and platform and uh for for us in
in flut that means uh building apps that
run on iOS and Androids uh on mobile
devices
building apps for desktop that's you
know obviously Windows Mac OS Linux and
building apps that uh also support the
web and being able to do all of those
things from a single code base being
able to do them all from uh one one set
of code which in the case of flutter is
uh people write their code in in doart
um and that targets all of those uh
different devices do you think we should
maybe tighten up the phrase or term
crossplatform development for cross user
interface platform development in this
yeah I I don't uh hugely like
crossplatform as a term because it
implies or historically has has implied
some kind of lowest common denominator
or uh an experience that's that is
limited we sometimes describe it from
our side as as multiplatform because
that sort of implies you know a slightly
different range of
optimizations and that's but but but you
know every word is overloaded in the
Computing industry I guess it does
actually make more sense to say
multiplatform was it multiplatform
development yeah multiplatform
multidevice to an extent you know we we
we go with the lingo the the
nomenclature that exists out there and
we uh everything is built on something
else right so I I think of flutter as
cross cross platform development without
compromise that's a much better
definition okay so if we if we sort of
take the various components that we've
mentioned there Windows Linux Mac web
and sort of bring it back to just mobile
for a few questions a minutes so there's
been quite a few different I don't like
using the word attempts but a different
quite a few different Frameworks over
the past what 10 years or so targeting
mobile um so you can have one code Bas
and
it bits out of version for iOS Android
uh Windows why do you think there's been
so many attempts and which brings me on
to where did flutter come from and dart
as well yeah well I think there's immens
it's an immensely attractive proposition
to be able to build an application that
can get to all of your customers uh at
once uh is is like one of those holy
Grails uh for uh Developers through the
through the years you know you're a
startup right and you're trying to prove
that your your great idea is is viable
it's it's critical that you're not
artificially limiting your access to
customers to just those that are running
a particular uh operating system or have
a particular brand of phone or you're an
Enterprise and you're trying to uh get
your customer experience uh out to every
customer at the same time with a
consistency of experience and quality um
again you know it's a very unusual
environment that I can't think of in
almost any other scenario that you'd say
to somebody hey you know we're going to
build three separate parallel payroll
systems for example that all going to be
developed have the same features and run
in parallel with one another so you know
UI is one of those uh areas where we
want people to be able to have that same
consistent experience uh at least in
terms of um you know releases and uh
time to Market and and quality uh
without the sacrifices that sometimes
come from that kind of experience and
that's that's really the value
proposition to use uh business language
for flutter to give you uh that that
ability to get a high quality high-end
experience to all of your platforms uh
simultaneously a little bit about where
flut came from um and dart which is the
language that you build fler
applications with they both stem from
the web actually there were two separate
parallel teams working on uh different
problems associated with web performance
uh and uh you know if you go back five
six years ago both the flut team and the
dart team were exploring how can we
build a better web how can we create uh
a better um software delivery uh
environment and for the D team that came
from Explorations around JavaScript and
virtual machine technology uh for the
flutter team that came from Explorations
around
uh UI presentation models and some of
the limitations of at the time uh HTML
and CSS as they then were and uh some of
those experiments uh were focused on uh
exploring what would happen if we
deliberately broke backward
compatibility if we said back backward
compatibility wasn't a goal for the web
what could that provoke in terms of
disruptive insights to how uh the web is
is created and you know not with
necessarily a goal to break the web but
but more to understand where the
limitations and barriers are in the web
as as we currently have it and that led
to a whole bunch of different insights
uh from which came both flutter and and
dat as as UI framework and uh
programming language and also uh
improved the web itself uh generated
insights that's uh create a better web
platform for all of us to build on and
that is of course the web that we have
today with with a high high quality um
pervasive experience so that's a little
bit about the story of of flutter and
dart to date and where did the the name
flutter and dart come from who who has
that oh that's a good question where did
they come from I think uh flutter came
from in part A company that we'd we'
bought uh it's it's very hard to come up
with brand names and trademarks that
don't already exist and uh so um flutter
uh I think we we we had a if you like a
a a name on the shelf that we had
already been through you know some of
our trademarking and you know domain
name uh purchasing and so that's that's
where flutter came from um actually
don't know where Dart came from as a as
a name it had an earlier name of Dash
and then it became Dart and I actually
it's a great question I don't know the
Genesis of that piece it predates me on
the dart team I'll Google it after this
and I'm sure I'll get a link for this
show notes yeah so that was a really
interesting comment you made about
forgetting see if I've got this right
forgetting the web as a sort of primary
platform and imagining it wasn't there
and seeing what you could do because I
understood the when you write the the
single Cod base in Dart and flutter that
the web output as it were of of of that
code when you build it was quite a
recent add-on and only in the in the
beta versions but the way you described
it there it was one of the first goals
or have I misunderstood yeah it's really
funny we've kind of come full circle
right we because we started with this
sort of presumption uh at least as a as
a presumption for for the project that
that breaking compatibility with the web
was the only way to deliver the
beautiful high quality experiences that
we wanted to be able to bring uh to
different platforms um but then as we
got uh closer and further into the
process the web itself has continued to
evolve and so now we've kind of come
back full circle and looking it uh how
do we bring flutter back to the web how
do we take the UI that you create with
flutter and translate it back to run on
the the web platform and of course the
web has progressed significantly over
this period of time we've we've made a
lot of progress in uh how the web has uh
evolved and uh uh you know the web web
has improved in its own access to the
underlying operating system web
continues to improve in terms of
performance and so we're seeing that
that's starting to also have its impact
in terms of how how flutter is able to
Target that um and so as you say we we
have started with flutter on on mobile
we we added uh uh early support for
desktop and web over the last year in a
preview mode and we're starting to find
that some of the improvements on the web
are enabling us to build surprisingly
high quality
experiences and that's using things like
wasm which is that sort of binary
compilation uh for uh for the web yeah
that's web assembly is it yeah the web
assembly uh experience um and then uh
canvas kit is a port of skia the the 2D
Graphics engine to WM and that lets us
get that full kind of opgl like sort of
experience uh for the web um without
sacrificing the performance that
inevitably comes from all the other uh
layers of things like the Dom and uh um
you know having to go through the the
traditional document orientated model of
the web yeah I was going to touch on
skia later on in the show because that's
what the rendering part of flutter is if
I got that right right if you drill down
through the layers of flutter what
flutter is essentially is a UI framework
that sits on top of a graphics engine
and skier is the graphics engine uh and
that in turn is what uh writes the GPU
instructions to actually physically uh
render content that ties us back
actually to a show we we did um I
haven't got a note of the number but
it's the one about writing software with
yval Lo because he speaks about um
architecting your software so all the
different bits or components and that's
what you B you basically did with
flutter is rather than have a primary
target you just made that are a
possibility the web's a possibility the
desktop's a possibility right yeah the
shift is is is like historically you
know when you start a new software
project your very first question
historically would be what am I building
right am I building a web app or an IOS
app or a Windows app and we want to
literally turn that question on its head
we want it to you to start with the
question of what do I want to build what
is my grand idea what is the design that
I want to create and make that uh
question about and what platform does it
run on we want to make that literally
almost the last question you ask in the
packaging phase of your software
development project and that's a that's
a huge kind of Paradigm Shift right it's
a very significant uh disruptive idea
but with tremendous potential for
shifting how apps are built yeah because
normally it's um right if I'm building a
mobile app I need to do it that way if
I'm doing a web app I do it that way and
it's completely not the right question
to ask you're like you mentioned earlier
it's what's the what's the business need
or the consumer need here and the rest
is a is a bolt on right I just wanted to
reinforce the comment you made about
creating the code base and then it works
on the web so I've been doing some
flutter apps you know just to get ready
for all this and did one and then ran it
so it SP out version for Google Chrome
and it just worked immediately I was
like oh my God this is amazing you know
I think when someone just picks up
flutter and runs the demos and reads the
the high quess of the documentation I
think that Penny just drops and opens a
whole I'm totally biased because I love
it but that's the benefit of being a
host you get to pick the topics you want
to talk
about so I think we almost finished the
introduction section we got a few more
minutes just to get a couple of
questions in before we start to roll up
our sleeves and get into the
architecture so could you give me a
couple of minutes on if Dart was created
at the same time or flut as flutter or
they were just parallel projects and you
tried a few other things you know what
would you say Dart is similar to and why
was it chosen yeah dart's a very
interesting uh language uh for a couple
of reasons it's it it was very much a
parallel project to flutter they they
they didn't start at the same time in
fact the very very earliest prototypes
of flutter use JavaScript as as the
programming language behind it and that
was really very much a distinct project
going on in a very different part of of
Google it was developed in Denmark by a
team in arus uh in in Denmark and uh the
uniqueness of was that part of Google
then or yes yeah just just a different
uh uh you know physical location way
outside of of you know the the Mountain
View campus as it were the things that
are unique about D are really
architectural and relate to its
technical envelope typically uh
languages focus on picking a particular
again a particular Niche you know every
language has its technical envelope the
space with which it's uh perfectly
suited you know go for example has been
very much uh driven by the needs of uh
server development uh JavaScript of
course driven by the web Java um
originally uh you know built around uh
this this jvm Java virtual machine that
has proven to be tremendously uh
valuable over the years but they all
impose their own uh restrictions
constrictions uh Specialties and and for
for darts the uh things that are pretty
unique about the dart technical envelope
relates to two things that I consider
some of the secret source of of flutter
firstly Dart is designed not around a
single Target uh compilation uh
environment so Dart supports both
production JavaScript
uh transpilation and compilation to
Native machine code whether that's arm
or Intel
x64 um so that ability to Target all of
those different uh uh platforms gives
dat a great deal of Versatility and then
the second aspect of dat is that it's
both designed around a high quality
development experience and a high
quality uh runtime production experience
and so we have these two different
compilers or two compiler modes for DOT
during development time we ship a small
VM to the the development Target and
that supports features like stateless
sorry stateful hot reload in in flutter
which means I can make changes to my
flutter code and I can just patch the
running code with the Delta and the VM
is able to uh just accept the the the
patch and and continue running the code
in real time and there are other
languages that do that right JavaScript
allows you to iterate and and make
changes in in in real time but what it
doesn't have is that production
compilation mode JavaScript is very much
designed around the a jit compiler that
is is there and is present interpreting
your code and so that's sort of one of
the unique sort of strengths of of of
dat as a language it it has this Matrix
of both web and Native compilation and
developer and and runtime um execution
and and it's that that that 2 by two if
you like of those those two different
things that gives Dart an envelope that
is really quite unique compared to other
languages I can't honestly think of
another language that offers production
quality support for for all of those
areas there are there are languages you
know that that that support uh
experimental modes there for example I
think C has a uh an experimental uh
transpiler to JavaScript but there are
very few that have that production
tested quality for both of those two
things and the fact that DT itself is
used by Google's ad framework for
example our our ad team uses dot for for
processing for for the for the the work
to enable um advertisers to to to bring
ads to different devices that means that
we've we've already demonstrated
millions of lines of of production
quality code transpiled to the web uh
similarly we have you know of course now
hundreds of thousands of of flutter apps
that are compiled to Native machine code
so again you know that's kind of the
uniqueness of of data as as a language
and its uh and its opportunity and AD
portion of Google is not a trivial
portion so that kind of highlights the
the quality of the of the chosen
language um do you have any comments on
the long-term goals or plans for flutter
at Google or is that just not something
yeah I mean one of the I think one of
the one of the kind of core principles
of Google uh one of those classic uh
statements is uh you know if we focus on
the user then the rest follows and
that's very much been our organizing or
sort of U cultural principle for for
flutter we want to build uh software
that that people love and use and
develop its road map and Direction based
off how people are actually using it so
we continue to invest in in this
broadening out across different devices
we're seeing a lot of excitement about
flutter on desktop for example lots of
uh cool samples I'm seeing and
prototypes that people are are starting
to build uh there the web similarly uh
so uh we develop in the open of course
we have an open issue log we look at the
top issues we look at uh real customers
and how they're using uh flutter and
dart and evolve based off that so I I
think you know you can expect to see us
continue to evolve the product based off
of those needs our immediate focus is of
course to get uh the various different
uh announcements we've made so far to
stable quality and those are desktop and
we Bond the flutter side and sound null
safety on the Dart side and so those are
the big immediate uh elements of our
road map yeah because you mentioned um
sorry you announced window support what
two weeks ago a we a week go the latest
version of the the the the alpha for for
window support yeah that's right and N
safety can you touch on that for a
minute yes of course yeah n safety is um
is that uh again one of those of classic
sort of uh language features that that
seems to offer tremendous promise uh of
uh being able to control whether
variables are are nullable or not uh and
there are quite a few languages that
offer uh support for non- nullability um
being able to prevent uh or being able
to express in the type that uh uh a
variable is is it cannot contain a null
value and the goal here is is primarily
minimizing errors right that null
reference exception uh that people will
be familiar with in many languages uh
has been the source of countless bugs
over the years um I think it's been
described as the as the billion dollar
uh mistake in the past um there are
there are good reasons for nullability
but but being able to protect against
that and guard against nulls appearing
where you're not expecting them is is
clearly valuable and again one of the
things that's rather intriguing about
darts implementation is that it's not
just expressed in the code but it's it's
a sound uh expression expression meaning
that the the type is is rified
throughout the uh lifetime of of the
code we're able to provably enforce uh
non- nullability
throughout uh the code so uh you know as
as you as your the flow of the pro
programming logic goes we can assert at
the compiler level that that there can
not be a null field in this type and
many language implementations
particularly those that have retrofitted
nullability or non- nullability uh are
not are not sound they they support it
but uh at runtime they still have null
detection in there because for think
reasons like reflection or other uh
language uh specification gaps they're
not able able to prove and assert that
that there cannot be a null in a
particular variable and we're just uh
getting this work mainstream just
literally last night as we record this
we have uh completed the work to bring
null safety into the flut framework and
our very very very early uh experiments
with simple examples are showing
performance improvements uh of the 5 to
10% range and the same for reducing size
of the code because we no no longer need
the instructions to guard code against
uh nullability I look forward to having
a play with that and possibly doing
another show on Dart by
itself okay I'm better move us on so
we're going to sort of dig into the arch
Aral flutter now the the guts of the
show mhm we've covered flutters history
where its name came from why Dart was
chosen how that developed and I won't
say cross platform development we'll say
multiplatform development now so I'd
like to get down to um the nitty-gritty
of what makes flutter
tick so what are the architectural
layers of flutter well I should preface
this by saying I'm a product manager not
a software architect so I kind of feel
uh humbled by your uh some of the other
guests you've had on the show that are
are certainly deeper than than I am or
of uh to deep don't worry but uh yeah
fundamentally at a at a high level
flutter is is built uh with what Ian
hickon our technical lead likes to
describe as the mahogany staircase and
uh the the principle here is that we've
built it as a as a series of layers and
each each uh step is self-standing in
its own right it's uh something that uh
does not have privileged access to the
layer below and so every uh layer is
theoretically uh optional and
replaceable so from the from the ground
up of course you know every platform has
its own core Primitives uh whether it's
something like openg GL or DirectX or uh
the layer that uh um that physically is
responsible for the interaction with the
underlying Hardware with flutter we have
uh a layer which which we call the
embedder and the embedder is responsible
for setting up the application platform
uh creating the inter leaving uh the
application with the underlying
operating system setting up threads
setting up the event Loop um handling
the creation of a render surface and uh
uh passing that across to uh the higher
level layers um handling things like um
passing Mouse input and uh touch input
depending on what device uh to the to
the higher levels just to ask a couple
questions about that level so there's
three layers in this I would say after
um some research and the embedder is
probably the the biggest abstraction
layer so it allows you to work with all
the different things that you're
targeting is that yeah the the embedder
is is is platform specific so we have
one of those for every platform we
target you know on Windows of course the
that is written in C++ Plus in on iOS
it's written in Objective C um and and
and so you know inevitably that is the
piece that is is utterly specific from
platform to platform and and that's the
the the bottom level of this framework
right yeah okay right now there's no
better time to learn a new database with
inner systems Iris you can build the
applications you want however you want
them you can connect your systems use
any data model and apply machine
learning so you can build data intent
ensive and Mission critical applications
in no time level up your skills with
inner system zis the fastest way to
build applications inner systems Iris
data
platform Ready Set
code visit inner
systems.com Iris to learn
more and um is the EMB better similar
to well we we'll speak about the
elephant the room react native is that
similar to those types of Frameworks
where they have JavaScript that breaks
into the the bottom layer through
channels or plugins native plugins as it
were yeah I'm I'm obviously no expert in
in react native my understanding of how
they uh work is that they provide
JavaScript as a as a language to Target
the underlying operating system which
would be similar place in the stack to
where Dart is possibly well I imagine
it's somewhat different because in in
react native you create for example a
button um but react native doesn't
provide that button um the JavaScript
code is telling the operating system to
present a button but I I have no real
concept of how that happens it's a it's
a it's probably a bad point to bring
that in um I just wanted to highlight
that the embedder is the bit that sort
of platform specific like you said right
great excellent and the the layer up
from that yeah so the so the embedder is
is again is is literally kind of like
the the bootstrapper if you like for the
for the application the actual rendering
takes place using the flutter engine
which is in the the desktop and mobile
uh versions is a C++ uh layer you can
see it if you go and that's the top
layer isn't it uh that's that's kind
like the middle layer if you like the
engine so if you go to GitHub you can
see there's actually a repo for the
engine itself and it's it's mostly C++
code the engine is responsible for the
actual physical kind of frame by frame
composition uh for for flutter code so
uh it takes the the whatever you write
at the top level which we'll talk about
in a moment um and uh is responsible for
compositing uh onto a physical surface
so it handles things like you know it's
time for a frame to be painted I need to
go and take the the various different uh
elements the render elements and uh uh
physically composite them on the screen
at the right resolution you know I need
to grab for example an asset or I need
to do a font uh uh layout and text
layout and rendering I need to be able
to handle an event like a a mouse or a
touch event and detect which which uh
element that that that affects so I can
bubble it back up to to the higher level
so that's the engine and say that's
that's the native code that's C++
compiled uh code uh that's is is a core
part of of the the flutter engine you
you as a as a flutter developer never
touch that of course it's the low-level
uh implementation that that implements
the work that uh that you you write so
the yeah the developer works in the
framework layer right which is the third
layer that's right so the the framework
is the actual the dot code that you can
typically see if you're using you know
an ID like Android Studio or Visual
Studio code uh and you you you click
into something like a button or or a
material app or a you know an animation
uh widget that's that code is written in
Dot and that's again compiled because
the doart code is compiled into uh the
uh underlying machine code and the
framework is responsible for
representing ing uh the engine to to
user code um and so it's that level that
has the the
core if you like developer Primitives
like animation or gestures or the widget
Library you know we we often sort of say
in flutter everything's a widget and
building blocks of everything that you
see in in flutter and so so you can see
that code it's is responsible for the
the orchestration of uh of you high
level widgets like uh a button into the
lower level widgets that uh or elements
that are responsible for rendering that
which of course includes you know maybe
a background rectangle and some text
that renders on top of that rectangle
and perhaps a shadow or something like
that um and that's what that's what the
framework level provides in flut okay
I'll just stick this all together so we
don't get lost so we've got flutter
which all of those three layers is that
yeah right and the three layers would be
the top which is the one that you work
in day-to-day as a developer which is
the framework which is pretty much Dart
en Dart yes yeah Dart all dart but it's
confusingly called the framework when
actually flutter is the framework of
everything right uh so that's Dart and
that's where we would sort of live and
breathe normally then the next layer
down is the engine which is written in C
and C++ yeah and that's responsible for
speaking down to the next level which is
the embed which is the platform specific
one so that has objectiv C for iOS is it
Java for Android or yeah mixure of java
and C++ on Android yeah C++ and then
windows will be C C+ C++ C C++ same for
Linux as well for yes yeah yeah and
those three layers make up the
flutter name as it were so in the dark
frame work we've spoken about widgets as
I understand a widget it's a name and it
has uh various parameters to that name
and and it does something is that is
that how you would describe a widget
well so a widget is really the the unit
of composition for for flutter it's the
it's essentially the building block uh
of of a flutter UI so it's it's
essentially a
declarative uh component that's that's
uh everything in flutter is built on so
again if I think of like you know a
typical the Hello World app if you like
for flutter typically there's there's a
material app which is this if you like
the the host application widget uh
there's a scaffold which provides the
kind of classic you know like a title
bar and maybe some some some tool barss
at the bottom and the the sort of the
canvas and material we're talking about
the material um user interface guideline
Google the material design system which
is which is one of uh of of a couple of
different ways you can build apps in in
flut but again it's the default so I
just picked that one up so material app
a scaffold that that itself is a host
for an app bar which might appear at the
top um a a the canvas itself of the the
main sort of body of the app and maybe
you know some buttons at the bottom
every one of those things are are
widgets but then if I take something
like that to that tab bar at the bottom
right that itself is probably a
combination of you know four or five
buttons that themselves are widgets
along with a a parent container that is
itself a widget and then if I drill down
into the button itself the button uh is
is probably composed of itself multiple
widgets you know an icon and some
supporting text and a background um so
you get the idea here really what we're
building up is is this sort of hierarchy
of of composition and it's the so that's
the kind of core organizing principle
for for everything builds uh in flutter
um when you create a widget you're
responsible for uh overriding the build
function to return a new element tree
and so if I create my own custom widget
or I create something like again a
material app what I'm really doing is
I'm representing the build method and
that method is called whenever there's a
change in the state of the application
to uh update the element Tre that then
flutter itself is responsible for
rendering yeah so if you if you imagine
you've got a let's take a mobile
platform an Android simulator you're
looking at the screen or you're looking
at your phone if you imagine every bit
on that screen is got a little rectangle
around it that would be each one of
those would be a widget or in in other
languages they call them components as
well and that's made up of several
widgets and the tree is that starts from
the bottom layer all the way up or is it
top down how does that tree work yeah
it's it's kind of complex but um and and
there's obviously you can the nice thing
is you could actually look at all the
source code because it's uh it's it's
this is all dart code right so you can
literally step through every element of
this but what's going on is when you
call the the build methods in or flutter
needs to re render something it calls
the builds method and that Returns the
sub tree of of widgets for uh that part
of the UI and uh as flutter does that
build it translates that into what's
called an element tree which is the
actual tree for for that flutter sort of
works on and so each of those widgets
themselves um have a mapping to a
corresponding element object um and some
of those are what we call component
elements that are that themselves are
are hosts for other elements that
gradually kind of get broken down um and
some of them are what we call render
object elements that are uh elements
that uh participate in the the layout or
the painting phases so that might be
something like you know uh a raw image
uh which is which is physically an asset
to be rendered on the screen and flutter
is responsible for doing that work of
translating all of those elements into
uh gradually into the uh walking the
tree until it gets to the lowest object
of a render objects which provides
flutter all that it needs then to say
okay now I can render this tree in real
time and so if you go into the uh
flutter Dev tools we've built some tools
that let you uh break down this the tree
and to see uh all of these see the
hierarchy of of widgets and how they
gradually are translated into into
elements but it's fundamentally that
rendery of the of the constructed uh
lowest level Primitives that are
responsible for for the actual painting
of of the of of the tree on screen yeah
the the development tools are a joy to
work with and like you said when you're
using one of the guies you can sort of
just click one of the widget names and
drill down as deep as you want it's
really nice um before I move on to some
other uh questions can we do a quick
example of say you've coded up a button
you click it and it launches the
fingerprint biometric or face
recognition part of your app and you're
using that type of plugin can you just
take us down from clicking that button
what layer that's at what it does in the
engine layer and then what happens in
the embedder not too deep but just to
highlight the the transition between the
yeah well um yeah and you're sort of
probing me to sort of the edge of my
sort of architectural sort of uh
knowledge a little bit here but uh I
think you're touching on a couple of
points there one is sort of how that uh
uh transition sort of occurs but then
the other part is how it talks to the
underlying native yeah I'm just trying
to sort of translate for the listeners
of how it speaks to this native part of
the platform specific but yeah yeah yeah
so we have this sort of concept of well
there are multiple ways to do it but but
we have a couple of ways to to talk to
the underlying Platform One is something
we call platform channels um and
platform channels provides a way for
flutter code or written in dots to talk
to platform specific code that might be
written in something like I know cotlin
or Swift uh or or C++ and what that what
that platform Channel model provides is
essentially uh a pathway for those two
components to talk to each other so my
my my C
dot code can send essentially a binary
message that is is essentially a
serialization of the dot uh um you know
parameter that I might want to send and
that is picked up on the other side by
uh the custom IO code that through from
the other end of this method channel so
that custom Android code would typically
have something like a an event handler
for when I receive this method call then
do this this work in in cotlin or or
Java
um and so that provides a relatively
efficient mechanism for passing um
States and uh um calls from from darts
to the uh underlying um Android or or
iOS or Windows code and then returning
obviously back to the to the flutter um
side um and so typically you'd use that
in in a in a mobile way if you look at
our package ecosystem we have I don't
know 15,000 package ages that are built
for for flutter um and typically that's
how they do things like as you say you
fingerprint reader or Bluetooth or
camera access or any of those um
underlying uh things we also have a
second model that is designed for for uh
C apis which is called ffi or foreign
function interface and that provides a
path for D code to to literally from the
same thread uh be able to access um uh C
or C++ code by getting access to the the
memory store if you like on the from the
Dart side to be able to interact with
the c code so for example I can create
um you know a struct or something like
that that that that includes uh um some
some uh State and pass a reference to
that struct to the C code and and vice
versa um and so that's kind of like a
deeper version of the same that's
perfect I just want to help the listener
translate that last level of how it
hooks into sure the base layer okay so
I've got quite a few questions to dig in
to now we've done that overview how does
the framework guarantee 60 frames per
second because that's something that
I've always read as the sort of a main
selling point yeah in fact the the the
framework itself doesn't make a
guarantee there what happens is that
whenever a frame is whenever the the the
phone or whatever device uh calls for a
new a new frame to be rendered flutter
takes that call and uh executes this
build process that I've sort of briefly
touched on and that's the build function
of the widget isn't it that's right
that's right yeah and and and so
everything comes down to um a fast
response to that build request right
assume just to simplify things greatly
assume the 60 frames per second is a
fixed frame rate that means you have
what 16 milliseconds is that right 16 *
60 is a th000 16 milliseconds for
everything to occur from receiving that
to uh having a new frame in the pipeline
for uh the the GPU to render and so if
you if you miss your window there if it
takes you longer than 16 milliseconds
the trains left the station as it were
you've you've missed your moment and
that's what generates you know sometimes
people call Jank or or that sort of uh
that delay um or glitching yes a screen
isn't it a Jun right right so so for for
flutter to be uh efficient and
performant it has to do that that stage
fast now of course we're we're calling
uh client code if you sit put a thread
sleep in there you're not going to be
done in 16 uh milliseconds uh but but we
have a whole bunch of like a lot of the
smarts in flutter is is around efficient
tree diffing to know what needs to be
rendered uh in that 16 millisecond slot
and so um if we're able to guarantee see
that only you know the the button that
you pushed for example has has changed
then that's the only bit of the build
method we need to call if we're able to
to be very specific around only
repainting the the elements that have
changed we can be we can be fast and and
that fast that speed isn't necessarily
60 frames a second it could be 120
frames a second it just comes down to
the performance of of the code and the
refresh rate of the phone and all target
device and that's why the general advice
is to keep widgets broken down into
small widgets with smaller build
functions or the framework can figure
out not to change that but or rebuild it
right there's endless optimizations that
you can make or not make it's possible
to build a bad application in flutter
just like any other uh framework um but
we provide you with both hopefully good
sign posting and Primitives to encourage
you to build uh a performance app and
also provide with you with tools to be
able to see you know you can actually
observe your your running application
you can profile it and see uh you know
when uh when you miss the Frame Window
you can drill down and see okay um I can
profile it and see well it was this
particular widget that that took longer
to render that pushed me over the limit
and typically what you discover is that
uh there's
a opportunities to make significant
differences to to how your code renders
for example if you have a key and it's
possible to show okay this this this is
the same as this from frame one to frame
two that makes the diffing much more
efficient I now know that these two are
the same thing so I don't necessarily
have to reender everything from scratch
or if I have a stateless widget that
contains stateful widgets and it's only
the state itself that uh it changes very
irregularly then flutter knows okay
that's the only bit I have to worry
about and so that's where a lot of the
magic really comes down to it at an
architectural level and that's two key
important bits I've neglected to ask
about is a
is a stateless widget and a stateful
widget yeah so a stateless widget is
simply a widget that has has no Changing
State you know it may may have things uh
on it like you know a text box that
might contain some text but if we know
that that text is not going to change
there's no it's a label we don't have to
worry about you know every frame asking
it have you changed and so that's that's
what a stateless widget is a state full
widget is essentially uh a widget that
uh has some mutability in time in terms
of the actual State itself um the the
mutability is is stored outside of the
widget because as I said earlier widgets
themselves are immutable but uh you can
call FL flutter with a set State method
to essentially signal the framework that
this uh widget now needs rebuilding and
that's what gives that uh that
flexibility there I understand and we've
we've touched on platform channels that
was one of my question and that's in the
the middle layer the engine I want to
ask about a dart isolate where does that
fit in compared to a platform Channel
yeah so isolates are how Dart does uh
it's it's threading if you like an
isolate is what all the dart code runs
in it's essentially uh uh space on the
on the machine with its uh with a single
thread running uh an event Loop and uh
many many doart apps actually just just
run everything in a single um single
isolates but you can you can create
multiple isolates uh if you if you want
to and they the thing that is sort of
Fairly unique about uh datart is that
each isolate is isolated right the name
is is the clue there and we try and kind
of create um a suitable sort of firewall
if you like between isolates um so that
uh there's you kind of avoid some of the
sort of the deadlocking and sort of
concurrency challenges that typically
come from multi-threaded uh programming
so in in flut there's a a function um
which is called compute that lets you
run expensive functions in a B
background isolate and return the
results so for example if you're you
doing some number crunching or you've
got you know an image that you're
processing you can move that work to a
separate separate isolate I just wanted
to highlight that sort of threading as
possible in that layer right yeah
absolutely which parts of these three
layers would you say does the most work
and which part is the hardest to get
right from a a flatter developer point
of view not the user as in me but for
you guys oh gosh uh that's an incredibly
difficult question uh to to answer I
guess um I I I mean the embedder itself
is fairly simple that that is that that
is is its goal is to kind of get in and
get out as fast as possible bottom layer
that's that bottom level yeah and so
that's that really is just setting up
the um the Run Loopers it were the idea
of the embedder is is is not that it's
sort of you know in integrated and and
and doing a lot of work each cycle right
in Windows you know that might be for
example the thing that sets up the
message Loop there's this sort of
classic sort of dating back to you know
the early 16bit days of Windows of a WM
message Loop that is passing messages so
the embedded respons responsibility is
to handle you know the WM Mouse button
down event say or something like that
pass that on to the engine but that's
all the has has all the Deep Machinery
if you like of of of flutter and um you
know clearly there's a lot of smarts in
the engine the framework in some ways is
is a little bit uh higher level just by
definition right it's it's it's
leveraging The Primitives of the engine
itself but it's a lot of code right
that's that's where a lot of the the
magic comes from flutter in terms of the
actual like everything that you
experience a flutter the the The
Primitives the principles of flutter
they they come from from the from the
framework and so you know there's
there's a lot of of of the interesting
aspects there and when you when you
shift to the web I haven't really talked
about the web much and how that that's
um uh engineered but in the web it's
just a little bit different because the
framework again is literally the same
framework we don't split the code base
there your your code is not the only
code that's the same across multiple
platforms our framework is itself
fundamentally the same uh framework but
what's different is is there's no uh C++
engine you know there's no kind of
active X control to use old terminology
uh on flutter the engine in the web view
is is uh simply an abstraction over the
underlying browser platform the web
browser apis and so the web version
that's that's all the code that exists
that is unique to the web is is exposing
the web platform engine to the flutter
dot framework that's a good enough
explanation for me so what do you think
or what do you know can't be done at the
lowest level of flutter so the embed is
there anything that you're still working
on or just isn't possible does that make
sense uh I don't think there's anything
that's not possible in as much as we FL
really is a native experience right so
everything that we do um is using the
same apis that you would build if you're
writing any other kind of native
application you know if I'm building a
Windows application in C I'm talking to
exactly the same API guys that uh I'm
using from flatter and I can use from
ffi with with dart so you know we we've
built sort of samples that use uh com
wind the windows runtime those kind of
like uh fundamental sort of Windows API
uh constructs from flutter you can build
with all of those different pieces the
pieces we're still working on are
exposing some of those things more
natively to Dart so for example you know
you mentioned uh things like um
touch or fingerprint recognition you
know you can call directly uh any of
those system services from from Dart
code but it sure would be nice if uh
there was some abstractions of those
features to you as a d Dart developer so
you don't have to know the underlying um
way that iOS or Android or Windows for
that matter implements fingerprint
readers um and so that's that's really
um you know as we mature the platform
and extend it that's where the package
ecosystem comes in um with those 15,000
odd packages that um provide commonize
abstractions or API representations of
those native and are those types of
things done through the platform
channels or if you're doing it in Dart
does that utilize the foreign function
interface or how would that you can use
either um typically if it's uh API in a
higher level language like uh cotlin or
Swift you'll use platform channels to do
them um if it's C C++ then ffi is a is a
very viable technique and um so my
little uh fun sort of evenings and
weekends project outside of my job as a
as a product manager has been writing uh
some of that abstraction Logic for
Windows given my history as a as a
Microsoft sort of Windows kind of person
um so I've taken uh you know the
hundreds of apis uh uh for some of those
core aspects in in win32 and written
Dart ffi um Primitives and any of your
listeners that are a c developer will be
familiar with uh things like pinoke and
there's a website called pinvoke.net
that provides um a translation if you
like from uh C to C that's essentially
what my win32 package does is provide
that same level of uh of binding from
dots to the underlying Windows logic
that explains why you were so excited
when you did the windows now ment about
two week yeah yeah it's fun to see these
different parts of my career join
together at last yeah it must be a real
scent of achievement couple of these
questions we've covered which part of
flutter creates JavaScript for the web
version that's just the EMB better I
think now as you've explained it well
actually it's a little more interesting
that because because again the framework
when you build a flutter app like when
you said you did your flutter uh run DD
Chrome what's happening is we're
actually taking taking the entire
flutter framework and compiling it to
JavaScript along with your dot code uh
for your own application all that gets
compiled into JavaScript and we do this
thing called tree shaking which is
essentially to discard all the bits that
that of the framework that your app
isn't using so you know if you're not
using um let's say animation in your app
then we discard all that stuff and we
only compile the bits that you actually
physically have in in your app and that
sort of creates this minified uh
JavaScript source file wow that's that's
not what I was thinking how it worked
excellent so what part of those layers
which I think we've answered already
should developers really get to know to
build a production flutter application
yeah yeah you don't need to know the
engine for sure right I mean that's sort
of that's the the swans the swan
swimming on the pond that's the legs
flapping frantically underneath the
water the bit that uh is well worth
getting to understand is the framework
itself and you know again that's sort of
like one of the one of the the little
benefits of flutter itself being written
Dart is that all of that code is very
much exposed to you so you you know you
never have to kind of second guess what
is the button doing what is a widget
doing you just read the source code and
indeed we encourage you uh if you know
widget doesn't do what you want to do uh
we encourage you to to just take it and
and you know copy it and uh uh you know
Fork it rather than necessarily trying
to do some awkward sort of subclassing
sort of kind of model so you know if you
if you need uh a button that's you know
PIV in 2.5d space uh and does fireworks
when you press the press the button you
can you can do that and all the source
is there to to do that you don't have to
you know wonder if the button itself
contains extensibility mechanisms for
fireworks yeah it's a I've said it a few
times already but it's a really lovely
experience when you're using a part of
the framework and you can just click
through to that layer and through to the
next cuz it's all there and just read
some really nicely written Cod as well
and get some ideas yeah I think uh that
sort of closes off for me all the
different layers and and how they fit
get together but I've got a few more
questions left over and then there's a
couple I've not done this on a show
before and I did give you a heads up but
I put a a request out to the flutter
Community to say that I was going to
have a chat with you and if they had any
question so yeah I've picked a couple
out of that but just before we get onto
that last bit I saw your Tweet uh last
week I think um about Google pay getting
Rewritten or has been Rewritten in
flutter yes can you take me through any
challenges you had in relation to the
architecture flutter or in general but
just maybe yeah two to five minutes on
it so we can yeah sure um a couple of
things that are interesting about that
and of course you know they're a
separate team um we've we've personally
I use Google Play App every day so it
was um was going to be really
interesting to hear oh okay yeah yeah um
so uh pay started some of this work by
pulling together a couple of different
uh apps they had a slightly different
experience for um a couple of their
their markets in in Asia I think India
Singapore um and there there was a
separately branded product originally
called Taz um tez um or tez I should say
um that was uh was was specifically
targeted at the India market and they
they worked working on bringing these
different uh variants of uh Google pay
together um and originally they started
a small project to uh look at whether
they could um add flutter sort of step
by step incrementally to their existing
app and they did a pilot uh project um
to see uh how that would play out and it
was one of those experiences where it's
a bit like the experimental drug that is
successful enough that you stop the
trial or you shift you shift like sort
of how the trial Works um they
discovered that they were actually
getting so much done in flut that they
decided rather than do an add to app
incremental migration approach they
decided no we're going to bite the
bullet and we're actually going to
rewrite the app uh in flutter um and so
they paused the the add to app
experiments and switched to a full uh
rewrite of the project which on the
surface seems like a luxury but really
what they were trying to get was that
agility of of development to be able to
build new features faster um and so what
you're seeing right now um at least at
the time of recording this in October
they are in open Beta I think in India I
think they've shipped the uh the new
version in Singapore and they're still
rolling out to other countries um so um
you know if you're in the UK or the US
you're probably still using the the
original version of the app um although
I don't know by the time this uh comes
out maybe you'll you'll you'll have it
but uh it's a it's a full rewrite
they've uh updated the user experience
for the latest material design uh
experiences and um as you mentioned they
wrote an article about it they've been
very very happy with their experiences
about this and uh maybe we'll we'll
write a little bit more about how they
built it yeah I look forward to those
articles so thanks for that I'm going to
move us on to some of the community
community questions in the last few
minutes of the show so one of the major
things that you have to deal with every
year is new versions of Android and
versions of iOS and either yeah
preempting them or catching up with them
yes so that was one of the questions
from the community but that was probably
about a month ago and it's now the
latest version of flutters out with with
ios4 support is there anything left in
the iOS iOS
14 ecosystem to support INF
flutter there's always stuff left uh I
think uh it's true of flutter as a whole
there's always more things that we're
sort of of you know we've got a a a list
of features to implement and uh
capabilities um that we want to support
the uh but every every release I mean we
as you say you know there's there's new
things that come out uh for flutter and
and that we need to implement in flutter
I should say for for those Target
platforms we we pay good attention to
both sides and now of course Windows and
Mac and others and uh usually there's a
little bit of advanced notice on on
Android of course we get significant
advanced notice because turns out they
they work for the same company um
sometimes any difference though does
it we work pretty closely with with
Android we're we're we're tracking
what's what's next um uh and on iOS you
know we we we find out at the same time
that everybody else does but Apple gives
you know a good few months notice of of
changes typically at dubdub DC and so um
you know we have a team that's focused
on uh adding those features as you
mentioned you know in iOS 14 they added
some new features like app Clips um
which are a bit like the Android instant
app support um they made some changes to
the UI um and and we we work on that
it's it's not insignificant amount of
work um but we need that work anyway for
our own apps like G like Google pay and
so uh you know our goal is to get uh
that work done so that you as a end user
don't have to worry about about that and
one of the nice things about flutter is
because again we we paint every pixel
ourselves we have control over the the
environment uh you get that uh support
sometimes going back as well so you know
sometimes you know material will
introduce a new component for example
and uh it's a nice thing about flutter
is that component becomes available as
we implement it for every version of
Android that's that's out on the market
not just you know the the version the
very latest version and so that gives us
I think a lot of uh resilience for for
the apps that are built with flatter
yeah because normally the argument for
going native is that it will get a a
look and feel refresh instantly but what
you've explained there is that you can
bring a modern look all the way back to
an older Android is that right right
right yeah and in particular you know
bugs that are fixed or changes or um
just those differences that occur as as
as technology moves on you know you're
targeting a consistent platform across
each of those different devices and so
long as the device itself supports you
know the the core engine Primitives the
skia sort of Primitives Etc that that
gives us significant flexibility to to
be able to push backwards and forwards I
would just say quickly though that that
you know we do want to encourage
developers to uh use the latest versions
of flutter itself right so as uh flutter
122 came out for example we added
support for some new system requirements
in apple uh apps uh for example relating
to text Fields there were some changes
in how they implemented that and so by
upgrading your app to flut at 122 even
if you don't actually make any changes
to your code self you just recompile
with flutter 122 you're going to get
some additional advantages and some
performance improvements on on the
latest releases yeah that's something I
do I did an app last year and almost
finished one this year and then just
rebuilding it with the latest f makes
tons of improvements over the previous
one yeah okay so summary of that is
you're happy with ios4 there was a lot
of um there was a lot of questions about
the demand or the wish for flutter to
work with goang is that something you've
heard about in Brackets I've got here
goes first class targets is that
something that you've heard in the Great
Vine or means nothing yeah we um it's
funny my very next meeting after we're
done with this is uh connecting with uh
my colleagues over and the go team we uh
see them as as kind of quite
complimentary uh because again you know
as as D is is uh We've explicitly
described it as a client optimized
language um I don't go would would be
quite so explicit in calling themselves
server optimized but they certainly it's
a it's a strength for them um and uh so
uh you know we we see those two as being
you know very interesting as as uh uh
com
something we should keep an eye on maybe
uh yeah I think uh um there's been some
interesting experiments also I've seen
go somebody implemented some uh
embedders for flutter using uh go uh to
try and again hit that breadth of of
platforms so there's there's all kinds
of little interesting interesting things
as part of that sort of interplay
between the two technologies excellent
um here's the last very specific
question from a Community member will
there be a tool to move components from
Angela Dart to flutter web oh
interesting yeah angular dot is uh uh
something we use a ton internally um you
mentioned ads right the ad um Center I
forget the name of the ad administrative
console that's all an angular dots app
um the Play Store um is built with with
angular dat it's a a framework that we
use primarily internally for um those
kinds of uh things um we uh make it
available externally as well um although
uh
it doesn't have the same level of
community support and interaction that
we have for for flutter we we sort of
somewhat throw it over the WM um we you
know we make it available to the to the
community but our aspirations for
angular dat is not that it sort of
becomes you know a flutter like sort of
uh you know broad open source project
but for those apps that are angular dots
you know that integration becomes very
interesting um and so yeah we're
exploring ways to maybe be able to embed
uh flutter web components in angular
doarts or po potentially uh uh vice
versa I don't know about tool for
automating um translation from one to
the other they're very different in
terms of uh Frameworks but but I but I
think you know as particularly as
flutter web starts to take off you'll
see a shift and support and um
componentization to make interplay
between those two easier it's like
anything in open source if it's out
there someone if they're interested
enough will do something over a weekend
and you know it'll blow everyone away
people do crazy things it's just I mean
you know even for flutter you know I've
seen examples of flutter running on um
you know Xboxes and flutter running on
embedded devices I know there are
companies that are using flutter in
things like fridges and microwaves as as
the way to you know show the smart
displays on there so yeah I love that
people do crazy things and sometimes we
look at those and we're like okay that's
actually a really good idea we should we
should build deeper support for that
into the framework itself I look forward
to reading some more about those okay
Tim I'm about to start wrapping up
although we can talk for ages on this
type of
stuff so obviously flutter is extremely
important for Google and has a very
exciting future but if there was one
thing a software engineer should
remember from our show what would you
like that to be oh I think uh I would
encourage people to listen to smarter
people than myself uh there's some great
talks from Folk like uh Ian Hixon who I
mentioned already that talk on the
mahogany staircase is a fascinating I'll
get that link in there sure not if you
can drop me an email after super yeah
absolutely um fascinating guide to to
you know again the sort of some of the
underlying architectural design
constraints but most fundamentally I
think I would just come back to that
original sort of comment right you know
our goal is to do something a little
different to what other historical
Frameworks have done uh whether they're
sort of system Frameworks or traditional
crossplatform frame works this this uh
fundamental shift of trying to build a a
native high quality experience for
multiple platforms um shifting away from
starting with your target platform to
starting with the application uh and
trying to give you the the tooling to
create that native high quality
experience on multiple platforms is the
thing that we see as our guiding vision
for flutter um it's a big you know in
some ways risky beted so far evidence
has been uh promising uh but we continue
to to build on that and uh you know
being open sources uh it opened a whole
world of interesting ideas for that and
hopefully we'll uh continue to develop
that along those paths for many years to
come and was there anything we missed
that you'd like to mention or thought
that would be mentioned uh I think
you've done a great job of pulling out a
lot of those interesting areas um maybe
one thing I'll just call out is the
community I think you know one of the
things that uh uh for us makes flutter
such a pleasure is this isn't a Google
project per se it's a Google sponsored
open source project um and so some of
the best aspects of of flutter have been
things that are seeded from uh the
broader open source Community the null
safety work that's going on has been
largely driven in terms of the migration
Itself by uh a non-google contributor
and there are many other examples of
that from big companies like Ali barar
um to Tiny uh you know single uh
individuals with a great idea that
they've implemented and that that makes
flutter bigger than anything that Google
can bring the majority of of
contributors to uh the latest release of
flutter came from outside of Google and
I hope that that continues uh for for a
long while to come I did like that when
you do I think you've been doing it for
a while where you do the release
announcement and the list the sort of
top 10 contributors and it's always
really impressive to see that they're
not Google people yeah yeah uh I just
one question before we go how big is the
team in within Google for flutter and
dart is that something you're allowed to
share or yeah I guess we have about a
100 people across flutter and dart
spread across engineering product
management marketing developer relations
um spread across flutter as a framework
dat as a lang language and a runtime
probably about 100 people that's that's
really cool um where can people find out
more um obviously they can follow you on
Twitter but if someone wanted to get in
touch what would you
recommend yeah um a couple of places uh
of course again being open source all of
our source code is on GitHub our road
maps our issue logs all of those things
are there and that's where the team
spends most of our time it's what drives
everything we do we don't keep a
separate you know backlog that isn't uh
the published GitHub backlog everything
that we do there is is visible also we
chat you can find us on Discord uh where
we have our various different
engineering chat rooms and that's sort
of the place if you're physically
contributing towards flutter or you have
a um a question about you know a feature
you're trying to add to flutter um
that's a great place to to
go okay Tim thank you for coming on the
show it's been a real pleasure this is
Gavin Henry for software engineering
radio and thank you for listening inner
systems iris is the fastest way to build
applications so take advantage of that
extra time on your hands and use it to
learn a new data platform deliver
complex Mission critical applications on
the fastest route possible with data
from any Source embedded analytics and
interactive user
interfaces with inner systems Iris you
can connect your systems use any data
model and apply machine
learning now is the time to level up
your database platform and try out inner
systems Iris so you can collaborate
build and deploy faster than ever before
don't wait any longer level up your
skills with inner systems Iris Ready Set
code visit intersystems.com Iris to
learn
more thanks for listening to SC radio an
educational program brought to you by It
software magazine for more about the
podcast including other episodes visit
our website at se-
radio.net to provide feedback you can
comment on each episode on the website
or reach us on LinkedIn Facebook Twitter
or through our slack Channel at seo.
slack.com you can also email us at team
e-r. this and all other episodes of SE
radio is licensed under Creative Commons
license
2.5 thanks for listening